Funding for this program is provided by
Additional funding provided by
This is a course about justice
and we begin with a story.
Suppose you're the driver of a trolley car and your trolley
car is hurtling down the track at 60 miles an hour.
And at the end of the track
you notice five workers working on the track.
You try to stop but
you can't. Your brakes don't work.
You feel desperate because you know that
if you crash into these five workers
they will all die.
Let's assume you know that for sure.
And so you feel helpless until you notice that
there is off to the right a side track.
And at the end of that track
there's one worker working on the track.
Your steering wheel works so you can turn the
trolley car if you want to onto the side track
killing the one.
And you can't.
But sparing the five.
Here's our first question.
What's the right thing to do?
What would you do?
Let's take a poll.
How many would turn the
trolley car onto the side track?
Raise your hands.
How many wouldn't?
How many would go straight ahead?
Keep your hands up.
Those of you who would go straight ahead.
A handful of people would.
The vast majority would turn.
Let's hear first.
Now we need to begin to investigate the reasons
why you think it's the right thing to do.
Let's begin with those in the majority.
Who would turn to go onto the side track?
Why would you do it?
What would be your reason?
Who's willing to volunteer a reason?
Go ahead.
Stand up.
Because it can't be right to kill five
people when you can only kill one person instead.
It wouldn't be right to kill five
if you could kill one person instead.
That's a good reason.
Who else?
Does everybody agree with that reason?
Go ahead.
Well, I was thinking it was the same reason on 9-11 we regard the people who flew the plane into the
Pennsylvania field as heroes because they chose to kill the people in the plane and not kill more people in big buildings.
So the principle there was the same on 9-11.
It's a tragic circumstance.
But better to kill one so that five can live?
Is that the reason most of you
had those of you who would turn?
Yes?
Let's hear now from those in
the minority, those who wouldn't turn.
Yes?
Well, I think that's the same type
of mentality that justifies genocide and totalitarianism.
In order to save one type
of race, you wipe out the other.
So what would you do in this case?
You would...
To avoid...
To avoid the horrors of genocide, you
would crash into the five and kill them?
Presumably, yes.
You would...
Yeah.
Okay. Who else?
That's a brave answer. Thank you.
Let's consider another trolley car case.
And see whether...
Those of you in the majority
want to adhere to the principle,
better that one should die so that five should live.
This time you're not the driver
of the trolley car, you're an onlooker.
You're standing on a bridge overlooking a trolley car track.
And down the track comes a trolley car.
At the end of the track are five workers.
The brakes don't work.
The trolley car is about to
careen into the five and kill them.
And now, you're not the driver.
You really feel helpless.
Until you notice, standing next to you, leaning
over the bridge, is a very fat man.
And you could give him a shove.
He would fall over the bridge, onto the
track, right in the way of the trolley car.
He would die, but he would spare the five.
Now, how many would push
the fat man over the bridge?
Raise your hand.
How many wouldn't?
Most of you would.
Most people wouldn't.
Here's the obvious question.
What became of the principle, better to save
five lives even if it means sacrificing one,
what became of the principle that
almost everyone endorsed in the first case?
I need to hear from someone who
was in the majority in both cases.
How do you explain the difference between the two?
Yes.
The second one, I guess, involves
an active choice of, you know,
pushing the person down, which, I guess, that person himself
would otherwise not have been involved in the situation at all.
And so to choose on his behalf, I guess, to involve
him in something that he otherwise would have escaped is, I guess,
more than what you have in the first case, where
the three parties, the driver and the two sets of workers,
are already, I guess, in the situation.
But the guy working, the one
on the track, off to the side,
he didn't choose to sacrifice his life any
more than the fat man did, did he?
That's true, but he was on the tracks.
This guy was on the bridge.
Go ahead.
You can come back if you want.
All right.
It's a hard question.
You did very well.
Who else can find a way of reconciling
the reaction of the majority in these two cases?
Yes.
Well, I guess in the first case, where
you have the one worker and the five,
it's choice between those two, and
you have to make a certain choice,
and people are going to
die because of the trolley car,
not necessarily because of your direct actions.
The trolley car is a runway thing,
and you're making a split-second choice,
whereas pushing the fat man over is
an actual act of murder on your part.
You have control over that, whereas you
may not have control over the trolley car.
So I think it's a slightly different situation.
All right.
Who has a reply?
No, that's good.
Who has a way?
Who wants to reply?
Is that a way out of this?
I don't think that's a very
good reason, because you choose to...
Either way, you have to choose who dies,
because you either choose to turn and kill the person,
which is an act of conscious thought to turn,
or you choose to push the fat man over,
which is also an act of conscious action.
So either way, you're making a choice.
Do you want to reply?
Well, I'm not really sure that that's the case.
It just still seems kind of different,
the act of actually pushing someone
over onto the tracks and killing him.
You are actually killing him yourself.
You're pushing him with your own hands.
You're pushing him.
And that's different than stealing.
You're steering something that is
going to cause death into another...
You know, it doesn't really sound right saying it now.
No, no, it's good.
But I'm up here.
It's good.
What's your name?
Andrew.
Let me ask you this question, Andrew.
Yes.
Suppose, standing on the bridge next to the fat man,
I didn't have to push him.
Suppose he were standing over a
trap door that I could open
by turning a steering wheel like that.
Would you turn?
For some reason, that still just seems more wrong.
Right?
I mean, maybe if you accidentally
like leaned into the steering wheel
or something like that.
But, or say that the car is hurtling
towards a switch that will drop the trap.
Then I could agree with that.
Fair enough.
It still seems wrong in a way
that it doesn't seem wrong in a way
that it doesn't seem wrong in
the first case to turn, you say.
And in another way, I mean, in the first situation,
you're involved directly with the situation.
In the second one, you're an onlooker as well.
All right.
So you have the choice of becoming
involved or not by pushing the fat man.
Let's forget for the moment about this case.
That's good.
Let's imagine a different case.
This time you're a doctor in an emergency room.
And six patients come to you.
They've been in a terrible trouble.
They're in a trolley car wreck.
Five of them sustained moderate injuries.
One is severely injured.
You could spend all day caring
for the one severely injured victim.
But in that time, the five would die.
Or you could look after
the five, restore them to health,
but during that time, the
one severely injured person would die.
How many would save the five?
Now is the doctor.
How many would save the one?
Very few people.
Just a handful of people.
Same reason, I assume.
One life versus five?
Now consider another doctor case.
This time you're a transplant surgeon.
And you have five patients, each in desperate need,
of an organ transplant in order to survive.
One needs a heart, one a lung, one a kidney.
One a liver.
And the fifth, a pancreas.
And you have no organ donors.
You are about to see them die.
And then it occurs to
you that in the next room,
there's a healthy guy who came in for a checkup.
And he's...
You like that?
And he's taking a nap.
笑い声
You could go in very
quietly, yank out the five organs,
that person would die.
But you could save the five.
How many would do it?
Anyone?
How many?
Put your hands up if you would do it.
Anyone in the balcony?
You would?
Be careful.
Don't lean over too much.
How many wouldn't?
All right.
What do you say?
Speak up in the balcony.
You who would yank out the organs.
Why?
I'd actually like to
explore a slightly alternate possibility
of just taking the one of
the five who needs an organ who
dies first and using their four healthy organs
to save the other four.
That's a pretty good idea.
That's a great idea.
Except for the fact that
you just wrecked the philosophical point.
Well, let's step back from these stories and these arguments
to notice a couple of things about the way
the arguments have begun to unfold.
Certain moral principles have already begun to emerge
in the history of the world.
And they are.
They are.
We have learned from the discussions we've had.
And let's consider what those moral principles look like.
The first moral principle that emerged in the discussion
said the right thing to
do, the moral thing to do,
depends on the consequences that
will result from your action.
At the end of the
day, better that five should live,
even if one must die.
Mm-hmm.
That's right.
All right.
That's an example of consequentialist moral reasoning.
Consequentialist moral reasoning locates morality
in the consequences of an act,
in the state of the world
that will result from the thing you do.
But then we went a little further,
we considered those other cases,
and people weren't so sure
about consequentialist moral reasoning.
When people hesitated to push
the fat man over the bridge
or to yank out the organs of the innocent patient,
people gestured toward reasons having to do
with the intrinsic quality of the act itself,
consequences be what they may.
People were reluctant.
People thought it was just wrong, categorically wrong.
To kill a person, an innocent person,
even for the sake of saving five lives.
At least people thought that
in the second version of each story we considered.
So this points to a second categorical way
of thinking about moral reasoning.
Categorical moral reasoning locates morality,
categorical moral reasoning locates morality,
and certain absolute moral requirements,
certain categorical duties and rights,
regardless of the consequences.
We're going to explore in
the days and weeks to come
the contrast between consequentialist
and categorical moral principles.
The most influential example
of consequential moral reasoning is utilitarianism,
a doctrine invented by Jeremy Bentham,
the 18th century English political scholar,
and the most influential English political philosopher.
The most important philosopher
of categorical moral reasoning
is the 18th century German philosopher Immanuel Kant.
So we will look at those two different modes
of moral reasoning, assess them, and also consider others.
If you look at the
syllabus, you'll notice that we read
a number of great and famous books.
Books by Aristotle.
John Locke, Immanuel Kant, John Stuart Mill, and others.
You'll notice too from the syllabus
that we don't only read these books.
We also take up
contemporary political and legal controversies
that raise philosophical questions.
We will debate equality and inequality, affirmative action,
free speech versus hate
speech, same-sex marriage, military conscription,
a range of practices that are not only
in the books, but also in the books.
We will also look at the philosophical questions.
Why?
Not just to enliven these abstract and distant books,
but to make clear, to bring out what's at stake
in our everyday lives, including our political lives,
for philosophy.
And so we will read these books,
and we will debate these issues,
and we'll see how each informs and illuminates the other.
This may sound appealing enough,
but here I have to issue a warning.
And the warning is this.
To read these books in this way,
as an exercise in self-knowledge,
to read them in this way carries certain risks.
Risks that are both personal and political.
Risks that every student of political philosophy has known.
These risks spring from the fact
that philosophy teaches us and unsettles us
by confronting us with what we already know.
There's an irony.
The difficulty of this course consists in the fact
that it teaches what you already know.
It works by taking what
we know from familiar unquestioned settings
and making it strange.
That's how those examples worked.
The hypotheticals with which we began,
with their mix of playfulness and sobriety.
It's also how these philosophical books work.
Philosophy estranges us from the familiar.
Not by supplying new information,
but by inviting and provoking a new way of seeing.
But,
but,
and here's the risk.
Once the familiar turns strange,
it's never quite the same again.
Self-knowledge is like lost innocence.
However unsettling you find it,
it can never be unthought or unknown.
What makes this enterprise difficult,
but also riveting,
is that moral and political philosophy is a story.
And you don't know where the story will lead,
but what you do know is
that the story is about you.
Those are the personal risks.
Now what of the political risks?
One way of introducing a course like this
would be to promise you
that by reading these books,
and debating these issues,
you will become a better,
more responsible citizen.
You will examine the presuppositions of public policy.
You will hone your political judgment.
You will become a more
effective participant in public affairs.
But this would be a partial and misleading promise.
Political philosophy,
for the most part,
hasn't worked that way.
You have to allow for the possibility.
The possibility is that,
that political philosophy may make you a worse citizen,
rather than a better one,
or at least a worse citizen
before it makes you a better one.
And that's because philosophy is a distancing,
even debilitating activity.
And you see this going back to Socrates.
There's a dialogue, the Gorgias,
in which one of Socrates' friends,
Callicles,
tries to talk him out of philosophizing.
Callicles tells Socrates,
philosophy is a pretty toy
if one indulges in it with moderation
at the right time of life.
But if one pursues it further than one should,
it is absolute ruin.
Take my advice, Callicles says.
Abandon argument.
Learn the accomplishments of active life.
Take for your models not those people
who spend their time on these petty quibbles,
but those who have a good livelihood
and reputation and many other blessings.
So Callicles is really saying to Socrates,
quit philosophizing, get real,
go to business school.
And Callicles did have a point.
He had a point because philosophy distances us
from conventions, from established assumptions,
and from settled beliefs.
Those are the risks, personal and political.
And in the face of these risks,
there is a characteristic evasion.
The name of the evasion is skepticism.
It's the idea, well, it goes something like this.
We didn't resolve once and for all
either the cases or the principles
we were arguing when we began.
And if Aristotle,
and Locke, and Kant, and Mill
haven't solved these questions
after all of these years,
who are we to think
that we here in Sanders Theatre
over the course of a semester
can resolve them?
And so maybe it's just a matter of
each person having his or her own principles
and there's nothing more to be said about it.
No way of reasoning.
That's the evasion, the evasion of skepticism,
to which I would offer the following.
It's true, these questions have been debated
for a very long time.
But the very fact that they have recurred
and persisted may suggest
that though they're impossible in one sense,
they're unavoidable in another.
And the reason they're unavoidable,
the reason they're inescapable,
is that we live some answer
to these questions every day.
So skepticism is the answer
to the question of
what is the answer to the question of skepticism?
And the answer to that question
is that skepticism,
just throwing up your hands
and giving up on moral reflection,
is no solution.
Immanuel Kant described very well
the problem with skepticism when he wrote,
skepticism is a resting place for human reason,
where it can reflect upon its dogmatic wanderings,
but it is no dwelling place for permanent settlement.
I've tried to suggest,
through these stories and these arguments,
some sense of the risks and temptations
of the perils and the possibilities.
I would simply conclude by saying
that the aim of this course
is to awaken the restlessness of reason
and to see where it might lead.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
And last time,
we started out last time
with some stories,
with some moral dilemmas
about trolley cars
and about doctors
and healthy patients
vulnerable to being victims
of organ transplantation.
We noticed two things
about the arguments we had.
One had to do with the way we were arguing.
We began with our judgments in particular cases.
We tried to articulate the reasons
or the principles
lying behind our judgments.
And then, confronted with a new case,
we found ourselves reexamining those principles,
revising each in the light of the other.
And we noticed the built-in pressure
to try to bring into alignment
our judgments about the reasons,
about particular cases,
and the principles we would endorse
on reflection.
We also noticed something
about the substance of the arguments
that emerged from the discussion.
We noticed that sometimes
we were tempted to locate the morality
of an act and the consequences
in the results,
in the state of the world
that it brought about.
And we called this consequentialist moral reasoning.
But we also noticed that in some cases
we weren't swayed only by the result.
Sometimes, many of us felt,
that not just consequences
but also the intrinsic quality
or character of the act
matters morally.
Some people argued that there are certain things
that are just categorically wrong
even if they bring about a good result,
even if they save five people
at the cost of one life.
So we contrasted consequentialist moral principles
with categorical ones.
Today, and in the next few days,
we will begin to examine
one of the most influential versions
of consequentialist moral theory.
And that's the philosophy of utilitarianism.
Jeremy Bentham, the 18th century
English political philosopher,
gave first the first clear systematic expression
to the utilitarian moral theory.
And Bentham's idea
his essential idea
is a very simple one.
With a lot of morally intuitive appeal.
Bentham's idea is the following.
The right thing to do,
the just thing to do,
is to maximize utility.
What did he mean by utility?
He meant by utility the balance
of pleasure over pain,
happiness over suffering.
Here's how he arrived
at the principle of maximizing utility.
He started out by observing
that all of us,
all human beings,
are governed by two sovereign masters.
Pain and pleasure.
We human beings,
we human beings,
like pleasure and dislike pain.
And so we should base morality,
whether we're thinking about
what to do in our own lives,
or whether as legislators or citizens,
we're thinking about what the laws should be.
The right thing to do,
individually or collectively,
is to maximize, act in a way,
that maximizes the overall level of happiness.
Bentham's utilitarianism is sometimes summed up
with the slogan,
the greatest good for the greatest number.
With this basic principle of utility on hand,
let's begin to test it and to examine it
by turning to another case,
another story, but this time,
not a hypothetical story,
a real life story,
the case of the Queen versus Dudley and Stevens.
This was a 19th century British law case
that's famous and much debated in law schools.
Here's what happened in the case.
I'll summarize the story,
then I want to hear how you would rule,
imagining that you were the jury.
The case of the Queen versus Dudley and Stevens.
A newspaper account of the time
described the background.
A sadder story of disaster at sea
was never told than that of the survivors
of the yacht Minionet.
The ship foundered in the South Atlantic,
1300 miles from the Cape.
There were four in the crew.
Dudley was the captain.
Stevens was the first mate.
Brooks was a sailor.
All men of excellent character,
or so the newspaper account tells us.
The fourth crew member was the cabin boy,
Richard Parker, 17 years old.
He was an orphan.
He had no family.
And he was on his first long voyage at sea.
He went, the news account tells us,
rather against the advice of his friends,
he went in the hopeful mood,
a world of youthful ambition,
thinking the journey would make a man of him.
Sadly, it was not to be.
The facts of the case were not in dispute.
A wave hit the ship,
and the Minionet went down.
The four crew members escaped to a lifeboat.
The only food they had
were two cans of preserved turnips.
No fresh water.
For the first three days, they ate nothing.
On the fourth day,
they opened one of the
cans of turnips and ate it.
The next day, they caught a turtle.
Together with the other can of turnips,
the turtle enabled them to subsist
for the next few days.
And then for eight days,
they had nothing.
No food, no water.
Imagine yourself in a situation like that.
What would you do?
Here's what they did.
By now, the cabin boy, Parker,
is lying at the bottom of the lifeboat,
in the corner,
because he had drunk sea water
against the advice of the others,
and he had become ill,
and he appeared to be dying.
So on the 19th day,
Dudley, the captain, suggested
that they should all have a lottery,
that they should draw lots
to see who would die
to save the rest.
Brooks refused.
He didn't like the lottery idea.
We don't know whether this was because
he didn't want to take the chance
or because he believed in categorical moral principles.
But in any case,
no lots were drawn.
The next day,
there was still no ship in sight,
so Dudley told Brooks to avert his gaze,
and he motioned to Stevens
that the boy, Parker, had better be killed.
Dudley offered a prayer,
and he told the boy his time had come,
and he killed him with a penknife,
stabbing him in the jugular vein.
Brooks emerged from his conscientious objection
to share in the gruesome bounty.
For four days,
the three of them fed on the body and blood
of the cabin boy.
True story.
And then they were rescued.
Dudley describes their rescue
in his diary,
with staggering euphemism,
quote,
on the 24th day,
as we were having our breakfast,
a ship appeared at last.
The three survivors were picked up by a German ship.
They were taken back to Falmouth in England,
where they were arrested and tried.
Brooks turned state's witness.
Dudley and Stevens went to trial.
They didn't dispute the facts.
They claimed they had acted out of necessity.
That was their defense.
They argued, in effect,
better that one should die,
so that three could survive.
The prosecutor wasn't swayed by that argument.
He said murder is murder,
and so the case went to trial.
Now imagine you are the jury.
And just to simplify the discussion,
put aside the question of law,
and let's assume that you as the jury,
are charged with deciding
whether what they did was morally permissible or not.
How many would vote not guilty
that what they did was morally permissible?
And how many would vote guilty
what they did was morally permissible?
How many would vote guilty
what they did was morally wrong?
A pretty sizable majority.
Now let's see what people's reasons are,
and let me begin with
those who are in the minority.
Let's hear first from the defense
of Dudley and Stevens.
Why would you morally exonerate them?
What are your reasons?
Yes.
I think it is morally reprehensible,
but I think that there is a distinction
between what's morally reprehensible
and what makes someone legally accountable.
In other words, you know, as the judge said,
what's always moral isn't necessarily against the law.
And while I don't think that necessity justifies theft
or murder or any illegal act,
at some point, your degree of necessity
does in fact exonerate you from any guilt.
Okay, good.
Other defenders, other voices for the defense.
Moral justifications for what they did.
Yes.
All right, thank you.
I just feel like in a situation that desperate,
you have to do what
you have to do to survive.
You have to do what you have to do.
You have to do what
you have to do, pretty much.
If you've been going 19 days without any food,
you know, someone just has to take the sacrifice.
Someone has to make the sacrifice,
and people can survive.
And furthermore, from that, let's say they survive,
and then they become productive members of the family,
of the society who go home and start like
a million charity organizations and this and that
and this and that.
I mean, they benefit everybody in the end.
I mean, I don't know what they did afterwards.
They might have gone and like, I don't know,
killed more people, whatever.
What?
What if they went home and
they turned out to be assassins?
What if they went home
and turned out to be assassins?
Mm-hmm.
You'd want to know who they assassinated.
That's true, too.
That's fair.
Okay.
I want to know who they assassinated.
All right, that's good.
What's your name?
Marcus.
All right.
We've heard a defense, a
couple of voices for the defense.
Now we need to hear from the prosecution.
Most people think what they did was wrong.
Why?
Yes.
One of the first things that I was thinking was,
oh, if they haven't been
eating for a really long time,
maybe they're mentally affected,
and so then that could be used as a defense,
a possible argument.
But if they're not,
then that's a good argument that,
oh, they weren't in the proper state of mind.
They weren't making decisions
they might otherwise be making.
And if that's an appealing argument,
that you have to be in an
altered mindset to do something like that,
it suggests that people who find that argument convincing
do think that they were acting immorally.
But what do you,
I want to know what you think.
You defend them.
Yeah.
No, no, no.
I'm sorry.
You vote to convict, right?
Yeah.
I don't think that they
acted in a morally appropriate way.
And why not?
What do you say?
Here's the thing.
I'm not saying that they were acting immorally.
I'm sorry.
You vote to convict, right?
Yeah.
I don't think that they
acted in a morally appropriate way.
And why not?
What do you say?
Here's Marcus.
He just defended them.
He said, you heard what he said.
Yes.
That you've got to do what you've
got to do in a case like that.
Yeah.
What do you say to Marcus?
That there's no situation that would allow human beings
to take,
the idea of fate or the other people's lives
in their own hands, that we don't have that
kind of power.
Good.
Okay.
Thank you.
And what's your name?
Britt.
Britt?
Yes.
Okay.
Who else?
What do you say?
Stand up.
I'm wondering if Dudley and Steven had
asked for Richard Parker's consent in dying,
if that would, would that exonerate them from,
from an act of murder?
And if so, is that still morally justifiable?
That's interesting.
All right.
Consent.
What's, wait, wait, hang on.
What's your name?
Kathleen.
So suppose they had asked,
what would that scenario look like?
So in the story, Dudley
is there, pen, knife in hand.
But instead of the prayer, or before
the prayer, he says, Parker, would you mind?
We're desperately hungry.
As Marcus empathizes with.
You're not going to last long anyhow.
Yeah.
You can be a martyr.
Would you be a martyr?
How about it, Parker?
Then, then would it be, what do you think?
Would it be morally justified then?
I don't think it would.
Suppose, suppose Parker.
In his semi-summit.
In his semi-stupor says, okay.
I don't think it would be
morally justifiable, but I'm wondering if.
Even then, even then it wouldn't be.
No.
You don't think that even with
consent, it would be morally justified?
Are there people who think, who want to
take up Kathleen's consent idea, and who think
that that would make it morally justified?
Raise your hand if it
would, if you think it would.
That's very interesting.
Why would consent.
Make a moral difference.
Why would it?
Yes.
Well, I just think that if he was making
his own original idea, and it was his idea to
start with, then that would be the only
situation in which I would see it being appropriate
in any way.
Because that way you couldn't make the argument
that he was pressured, you know, it's three
to one or whatever the ratio was.
Right.
And I think that if he was making a decision
to give his life, then he took on the agency,
to sacrifice.
Right.
To sacrifice himself, which some people might
see as admirable, and other people might disagree
with that decision.
So if he came up with the idea, that's
the only kind of consent we could have confidence
in morally, then it would be okay.
Otherwise it would be kind of
coerced consent under the circumstances, you think.
Is there anyone who thinks that even the consent.
The consent of Parker would not justify their killing him?
Who thinks that?
Yes.
Tell us why.
Stand up.
I think that Parker would be killed with
the hope that the other crew members would be
rescued.
So there's no definite reason that he should
be killed because you don't know who, when
they're going to get rescued.
So if you kill him, it's killing him in vain.
Do you keep killing the crew member until
you're rescued and then you're left with no
reason?
No.
Because someone's going to die eventually.
Well, the moral logic of the situation seems
to be that, that they would keep on picking
off the weakest, maybe, one
by one, until they were rescued.
And in this case, luckily, they were
rescued when three at least were still alive.
Now if Parker did give his consent, would
it be all right, do you think, or not?
No.
It still wouldn't be right.
And tell us why it wouldn't be all right.
First of all, cannibalism, I believe, is morally incorrect.
So you shouldn't be eating a human anyway.
So cannibalism is morally objectionable.
So then, even on the scenario of waiting
until someone died, still it would be objectionable.
Yes.
To me personally.
I feel like it all depends on one's personal
morals and we can't sit here and just, this
is just my opinion.
And of course, other people are going to disagree.
Well, we'll see.
Let's see what their disagreements are and then
we'll see if they have reasons that can
persuade you or not.
Let's try that.
All right.
Let's, now, is there someone who can explain,
those of you who are tempted by consent, can
you explain why consent makes such a moral difference?
What about the lottery idea?
Does that count as consent?
Remember, at the beginning, Dudley proposed a lottery.
Suppose that they had agreed to a lottery.
Then, how many would then say it was all right?
Suppose there were a lottery, cabin boy
lost, and the rest of the story unfolded.
Then how many people would say it was morally permissible?
So the numbers are rising if we add a lottery.
Let's hear from one of you.
Let's hear from you.
For whom the lottery would make a moral difference.
Why would it?
I think the essential element, in my mind, that
makes it a crime is the idea that they
decided at some point that their lives were
more important than his and that, I mean,
that's kind of the basis for really any crime, right.
It's like, my needs, my desires are
more important than yours and mine take precedent.
And if they had done a lottery where
everyone consented that someone should die and it's,
right, that's a crime.
it's sort of like they're all
sacrificing themselves to save the rest.
Then it would be all right.
A little grotesque, but...
But morally permissible?
Yes.
And what's your name?
Matt.
So, Matt, for you,
what bothers you is not the cannibalism,
but the lack of due process.
I guess you could say that.
Right?
And can someone who agrees with Matt
say a little bit more
about why a lottery
would make it, in your view,
morally permissible?
Go ahead.
The way I understood it originally
was that that was the whole issue,
is that the cabin boy was never consulted
about whether or not something
was going to happen to him,
even with the original lottery,
whether or not he would be a part of that.
It was just decided,
that he was the one that was going to die.
Right.
That's what happened in the actual case.
But if there were a lottery
and they'd all agreed to the procedure,
you think that would be okay?
Right.
Because then everyone knows
that there's going to be a death.
Whereas, you know,
the cabin boy didn't know
that this discussion was even happening.
There was no, you know, forewarning
for him to know that,
hey, I may be the one that's dying.
All right.
Now, suppose everyone agrees to the lottery,
they have the lottery,
the cabin boy loses,
and he changes his mind.
Right.
You've already decided.
It's like a verbal contract.
You can't go back on that.
You've decided the decision was made.
You know, if you know that you're dying
for the, you know, the reason for others to live,
you would, if someone else had died,
you know that you would consume them.
So, that's what...
Right.
But then he could say,
I know, but I lost.
I just think that that's the whole moral issue
is that there was no consulting of the cabin boy
and that that's what makes it the most,
horrible is that he had no
idea what was even going on.
That had he known what was going on,
it would be a bit more understandable.
All right.
Good.
Now, I want to hear,
so there are some who think it's morally permissible,
but only about 20%.
Led by Marcus.
Then there are some who say,
the real problem here is the lack of consent.
Whether the lack of consent,
to a lottery, to a fair procedure,
or, Kathleen's idea,
lack of consent at the moment of death.
And if we add consent,
then more people are willing to consider
the sacrifice morally justified.
I want to hear now, finally,
from those of you who think,
even with consent,
even with a lottery,
even with a final,
murmur of consent by Parker,
at the very last moment,
it would still be wrong.
And why would it be wrong?
That's what I want to hear.
Yes.
Well, the whole time I've been leaning all towards
the categorical moral reasoning.
And I think that there's a possibility I'd be okay
with the idea of a lottery,
and then the loser taking it into their own hands
to kill themselves.
Um.
So there wouldn't be, you know, an act of murder.
But I still think that,
even that way, it's coerced.
And, um, also, I don't think that there's any remorse.
Like in Dudley's diary,
we were eating our breakfast.
It seems as though he's just sort of like,
um, you know, the whole idea
of not valuing someone else's life.
So that makes me feel like
I have to take the categorical stand.
You want to throw the book at him.
When he lacks remorse or a
sense of having done anything wrong.
Right.
So, all right, good.
Other, any other defenders of a, uh,
who say it's just categorically wrong,
with or without consent?
Yes, stand up.
Why?
I think undoubtedly to where our society is shaped,
murder is murder.
Murder is murder in every way.
And our society looks at murder
down on it in the same light.
And I don't think it's any different in any case.
Good.
Let me ask you a question.
There were three lives at stake.
Mm-hmm.
Versus one.
Okay.
The one, the cabin boy, he had to.
He had no family.
He had no dependents.
These other three had families back home in England.
They had dependents.
They had wives and children.
Think back to Bentham.
Bentham says we have to consider the welfare, the utility,
the happiness of everybody.
We have to add it all up.
So it's not just numbers three against one.
It's also all of those people at home.
In fact, the London newspaper at the time,
and popular opinion,
they didn't sympathize with them,
Dudley and Stephens.
And the paper said if they weren't motivated by affection
and concern for their loved ones at home
and their dependents, surely they wouldn't have done this.
Yeah, and how is that any different
from people on the corner trying to have
the same desire to feed their family?
I don't think it's any different.
I think in any case, if I'm murdering you
to advance my status, that's murder.
And I think that we should look
at that all in the same light.
Instead of criminalizing certain activities,
and making certain things seem like they're not, you know,
and making certain things seem more violent and savage,
when in the same case, it's all the same.
It's all the same act
and mentality that goes into murder,
necessity to feed your family, so.
Suppose it weren't three, suppose it were 30.
One life to save 300.
We're in war time.
Suppose the stakes are even bigger.
I think it's still the same deal.
Do you think Bentham is wrong
to say the right thing to do
is to add up the collective happiness?
Do you think he's wrong about that?
I don't think he's wrong,
but I think murder is murder in any case.
Well, then Bentham has to be wrong.
If you're right, he's wrong.
Okay, then he's wrong.
All right.
I'm right.
Thank you, well done.
All right, let's step back from this discussion,
and notice how many objections have we heard
to what they did.
We heard some defenses of what they did.
The defenses had to do with necessity,
their dire circumstance,
and implicitly at least, the idea that numbers matter.
And not only numbers matter, but the wider effects matter.
Their families back home, their dependents.
Parker was an orphan.
No one would miss him.
So if you add up, if you try to calculate
the balance of happiness and suffering,
you might have a case for saying
what they did was the right thing.
And then we heard at
least three different types of objections.
We heard an objection that said,
what they did was categorically wrong.
Mike here at the end.
Categorically wrong.
Murder is murder, it's always wrong,
even if it increases the overall happiness of society.
A categorical objection.
But we still need to investigate
what they did was categorically wrong.
And that's what we're going to do.
We're going to investigate
why murder is categorically wrong.
Is it because even cabin
boys have certain fundamental rights?
And if that's the reason,
where do those rights come from,
if not from some idea of the larger welfare,
or utility, or happiness?
Question number one.
Others said a lottery would make a difference.
A fair procedure.
A fair procedure, Matt said.
But, and some people were swayed by that.
That's not a categorical objection exactly.
It's saying everybody has to be counted as an equal,
even though at the end of the day,
one can be sacrificed for the general welfare.
That leaves us with another question to investigate.
Why does agreement to a certain procedure,
even a fair procedure, justify whatever result flows
from the operation of that procedure?
Question number two.
And question number three, the basic idea of consent.
Kathleen got us onto this.
If the cabin boy had agreed himself,
and not under duress, as was added,
then it would be all right to take his life.
He would have had to take
his life to save the rest.
And even more people signed onto that idea.
But that raises a third philosophical question.
What is the moral work that consent does?
Why does an act of
consent make such a moral difference
that an act that would be
wrong, taking a life without consent,
is morally permissible with consent?
To investigate those three questions,
we're going to have to read some philosophers.
And starting next time, we're going to read
Bentham and John Stuart Mill, utilitarian philosophers.
Don't miss the chance to interact online
with other viewers of Justice.
Join the conversation. Take a pop quiz.
Watch lectures you've missed and learn a lot more.
Visit justiceharvard.org. It's the right thing to do.
We'll see you next time.
Funding for this program is provided by...
Additional funding provided by...